Guide to the Roland L. Freeman Photographs, 1969-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Roland L. Freeman photographs 1969-1985
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Freeman, Roland L., 1936-
2.0 linear feet Extent: 12 Items
American photographer devoted to recording the lives of rural and urban African Americans. Collection consists of Freeman's Portfolio, a 1997 limited edition portfolio of twelve 16x20 gelatin silver prints depicting everyday life in the South, dating 1969-1985. This Portfolio is Number 33 of 45. Prints include Freeman's signature on the bottom right corner. Accompanying pamphlet includes essays about the photographer and a title list for the photographs. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University).
freemanroland
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is restricted to educational, non-commercial use. Creator retains all copyright.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Roland L. Freeman Photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2009.
Biographical Note
Roland L. Freeman, a native of Baltimore, Maryland, is the founder and president of The Group for Cultural Documentation, Inc. He began his photography career in the 1960s during the Civil Rights Movement. Freeman's interest in documenting people, particularly African Americans, has centered on folklore and everyday life. He has worked with the Smithsonian Center for Folklife and Cultural Heritage since 1972, and has taught and lectured at universities throughout the country. In addition, his photography has been published in Life, Newsweek, Forbes, National Geographic, Essence, as well as numerous international publications. His photographs have also been exhibited throughout the world.
Freeman's books include Something To Keep You Warm: The Roland Freeman Collection of Black American Quilts from the Mississippi Heartland (1979), Southern Roads/City Pavements: Photographs of Black Americans (1981), Stand By Me: African American Expressive Culture in Philadelphia (1989), The Arabbers of Baltimore (1989), Margaret Walker's 'For My People': A Tribute (1992), A Communion of the Spirits: African-American Quilters, Preservers, and Their Stories (1996), and The Mule Train: A Journey of Hope Remembered (1998). In 2007, he was awarded a National Endowment for the Arts National Heritage Fellowship, along with the NEA's Bess Lomax Hawes Award.
More information on Roland Freeman can be found on The Group for Cultural Documentation's website, http://www.tgcd.org/.
Collection Overview
Collection consists of Freeman's Portfolio, a 1997 limited edition portfolio of twelve 16x20 gelatin silver prints depicting everyday life in the South, dating 1969-1985. Areas represented include Maryland, Mississippi, South Carolina, Georgia, Alabama, and Washington, D.C. This Portfolio is Number 33 of 45. Prints include Freeman's signature on the bottom right corner. Accompanying pamphlet includes essays about the photographer and a title list for the photographs. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University).
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Freeman, Roland L., 1936-; Freeman, Roland L., 1936-. Portfolio; Documentary photography -- Southern states; Mississippi-Pictorial works; Maryland -- Pictorial works; South Carolina -- Pictorial works; Georgia -- Pictorial works; Alabama -- Pictorial works; Gelatin silver prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Related Material
The Roland L. Freeman Papers are held by the Auborn Avenue Research Library on African American Culture and History, a division of the Atlanta-Fulton Public Library System.
Contents of Collection
- Portfolio, 1997, (1 box)
  Photographs date from 1969-1985. Title list included below.
  - Peter, East Baltimore, June 1969 (Box 1)
  - Community elders, Mississippi, July 1975
  - Cigar box fiddler Scott Dunbar, Mississippi, July 1975
  - Gandy dancers (railroad workers), Mississippi, August 1976
  - Sunday baseball game, near Buffalo, Mississippi, September 1976
  - Shopping on Gay Street, East Baltimore, Maryland, 1973
  - Left to right: Ruby Quick, Wilford Streeter, and Claudie Mae Bright. In the sand hills, near Bennettsville, South Carolina, 1979
  - Hallway of Polk home, Americus, Georgia, April 1971
  - Getting acquainted, Sunday afternoon in Druid Hill Park, Baltimore, Maryland, August 1973
  - Howard University student, Washington, D.C., June 1979
  - Before Sunday evening service, St. Helena Island, South Carolina, June 1980
  - Mrs. Viola Allen, Africatown, Alabama, November 1985